Hi and welcome back to Rock the JVM's Scala at Lightspeed. I'm Daniel and in
はい、Rock the JVMの「Scala at Lightspeed」にようこそ。Danielだよ。
this video we will discuss functional programming in Scala. Now I'm gonna get
この動画ではScalaの関数型プログラミングについて話していくよ。じゃあ
back to our project that we started in an earlier video and I'm going to
前の動画で作ったプロジェクトに戻って
continue with a dedicated application specifically for this video. So I will
この動画専用のアプリケーションを作っていくね。
assume that you've watched the rest of the series so far, if you haven't go back
ここまでのシリーズを見てる前提で進めるから、まだ見てない人は
and watch that because we discussed the fundamentals that we are going to use in
戻って見てきてね。この動画で使う基礎的な内容を
this video. So I'm gonna click on rock.com.rock.jvm and I'm going to create a
そこで解説してるからね。じゃあ rock.com.rock.jvm をクリックして
new Scala application. So right click new Scala class. I'm gonna name this
新しいScalaアプリケーションを作るよ。右クリックしてNew Scala class。名前は
functional programming and I'm going to make it an object as before and I'm
FunctionalProgrammingにして、前と同じように object にするよ。
going to make it extend app. So extends app. In the previous video where we
そして extends App にする。extends App ね。前回のオブジェクト指向の動画で
discussed object orientation you understood what an object is and what
object が何なのか、extends App が何を意味するのか
extends app meant. Now before we discuss functional programming it's worth
理解したよね。さて、関数型プログラミングの話に入る前に
recapping some very important points that I will be using when proving some
この動画で関数型プログラミングの原則を説明するときに使う
functional programming principles here in Scala. So we know that Scala is an
とても重要なポイントをおさらいしておこう。Scalaはオブジェクト指向の
object-oriented language. In the sense that we can define a class let's call this
言語だよね。つまり、クラスを定義できる。例えば
person for example and the person class can have some constructor arguments for
Personっていうクラスを作ると、コンストラクタ引数を持てる。
example the person can have a name as a string and Scala has this very nice apply
例えばnameをStringで持てるし、Scalaにはとても便利なapplyっていう
special method. So if you define an apply method to a class let's have for example an age as an int and this
特別なメソッドがあるんだ。applyメソッドをクラスに定義すると、例えばageをIntで受け取って
prince line I have aged age years. All right so if I define an apply method that looks something like this an apply method that takes some constructor arguments and if I create an instance of this class let's say I create an instance called Bob as new person
println("I have aged " + age + " years") みたいにする。で、こういうapplyメソッドを定義して、引数を受け取るapplyメソッドがあるとする。このクラスのインスタンスを作って、例えばBobっていうインスタンスをnew Personで
with the name Bob I can call bob dot apply with age 43 or I can simply say bob applied to 43 so I'm basically invoking bob as a function this actually signals to the compiler that I'm actually going calling the apply method so this is equal to bob dot apply with the argument 43 so the present
名前を"Bob"にする。そうすると bob.apply(43) って呼べるし、単に bob(43) って書ける。つまりbobを関数みたいに呼び出してるんだ。これは実際にはコンパイラにapplyメソッドを呼んでるって伝えてる。だから bob(43) は bob.apply(43) と同じなんだよ。
the presence of an apply method allows an instance of an apply method allows an instance of a class to be invoked like a function now this is important why is that Scala runs on the JVM
applyメソッドがあることで、クラスのインスタンスを関数のように呼び出せるんだ。これが重要な理由は、ScalaがJVM上で動くからなんだよね。
So the Java virtual machine is the infrastructure on which all Java programs run and there are many languages that compiled to Java virtual machine by code like Scala but the JVM was fundamentally built for Java which is the prototypical object oriented language and so the JVM knows what an object is but it doesn't know what a function is as a first class citizen what do we mean by that in functional programming
Java仮想マシンっていうのは、すべてのJavaプログラムが動くインフラなんだ。ScalaみたいにJVMのバイトコードにコンパイルされる言語はたくさんあるけど、JVMは基本的にJavaのために作られたもので、Javaは典型的なオブジェクト指向言語だよね。だからJVMはオブジェクトが何かは知ってるけど、関数を第一級市民として扱う方法は知らない。これはどういう意味かっていうと、関数型プログラミングでは
we want to work with functions as we want to work with functions as what we call first class elements of programming what do we mean by that we want to be able to work with functions like we work with any other kind of values so we want to compose functions
関数をいわゆるプログラミングの第一級要素として扱いたいんだ。どういうことかっていうと、関数を他の値と同じように扱いたい。関数を合成したり、
and return functions as arguments
関数を引数として渡したり
and return functions as results
関数を結果として返したり
the kind of stuff that we normally operate on when we work with objects or plain values so we want to do that with functions as well so because the JVM was not fundamentally built for functional programming it was built for object oriented programming how do we implement functional programming on the JVM and the result was that the Scala people invented the JVM.
オブジェクトや普通の値に対して普段やってることと同じことを関数でもやりたいわけ。でもJVMは関数型プログラミングのために作られたんじゃなくて、オブジェクト指向のために作られた。じゃあJVM上でどうやって関数型プログラミングを実現するか？
And the result was that the Scala people invented some very very interesting and very clever traits called function X.
その答えとして、Scalaの人たちがFunctionXっていうすごく賢いtraitを発明したんだ。
Let me give you an example. Let me define a small function that I'm going to call simple incrementer as a new and here's what I'm going to write. I'm going to write function 1 typed with int and int, that is a function that takes an int and returns an int.
例を見せるね。simpleIncrementerっていう小さな関数を定義するよ。new って書いて、Function1[Int, Int]って書く。これはIntを受け取ってIntを返す関数だよ。
This is just a plain trait with an apply method. So if I create an apply that takes the argument as an int and returns the argument plus 1, I have defined an instance of this function 1 trait. And then I can call simple incrementer dot apply with the argument let's say 23 and I would return 24, right?
これは単にapplyメソッドを持つtraitなんだ。applyメソッドで引数をIntで受け取って argument + 1 を返すようにすれば、このFunction1 traitのインスタンスを定義したことになる。そしたら simpleIncrementer.apply(23) って呼べば24が返ってくるよね？
Because simple incrementer dot apply takes 23 and returns 23 plus 1. But I can simply call simple incrementer on 23 and this is the same as calling the apply method.
simpleIncrementer.apply は23を受け取って23 + 1を返すから。でも単に simpleIncrementer(23) って書けば、applyメソッドを呼ぶのと同じことなんだ。
So what have we done here? We have instantiated this trait that we call function 1 but ignore the name for now. The function 1 name is not important. We've just instantiated a trait.
じゃあここで何をしたかっていうと、Function1っていうtraitをインスタンス化したんだ。名前は今は気にしなくていいよ。Function1っていう名前は重要じゃない。単にtraitをインスタンス化しただけ。
So the function that we have created can be invoked like a function because it has an apply method and the only thing that it supports is to be invoked like a function.
作った関数はapplyメソッドを持ってるから関数みたいに呼び出せるし、できることは関数として呼び出されることだけなんだ。
So we've basically defined a function.
つまり、関数を定義したってことなんだよ。
Because it acts like a function and the only thing that it can do is act like a function. It takes a bunch of arguments and it returns something else.
関数として振る舞うし、できることは関数として振る舞うことだけ。引数を受け取って何かを返す。
So the conclusion that I want you to take away from this video is that all Scala functions are instances of these function x type.
この動画で覚えておいてほしい結論は、Scalaのすべての関数はFunctionX型のインスタンスだってこと。
So the way that we've implemented a functional language on top of the JVM which is fundamentally built for object orientation is to make functions actually instances of this function 1, function 2, function 3, and so on and so forth traits.
つまり、基本的にオブジェクト指向のために作られたJVMの上に関数型言語を実装した方法は、関数を実際にはFunction1、Function2、Function3とかのtraitのインスタンスにすることだったんだ。
So this function x means function 1, function 2, all the way to function 22. So 22 is the maximum number of arguments that you can pass to a function.
FunctionXっていうのはFunction1、Function2、Function22までのこと。22が関数に渡せる引数の最大数なんだ。
And all the Scala functions that we define are actually instances of this function x trait.
定義するScalaの関数はすべて、実際にはこのFunctionX traitのインスタンスなんだよ。
Just as another example, if I define a string concatenator as a function that takes two strings and returns another string, we can define a function 2, which takes two type arguments, string string, and the third type argument is the return type, which is string.
もう一つ例を出すね。stringConcatenatorっていう、2つのStringを受け取って別のStringを返す関数を定義するとする。Function2で、型引数がString、String、そして3つ目の型引数が戻り値の型でStringになる。
And the apply method takes arg1 as a string and arg2 as a string and returns, for example, arg1 plus arg2.
applyメソッドはarg1をString、arg2をStringで受け取って、例えばarg1 + arg2を返す。
In much the same way, we can simply apply this function, this string concatenator, on multiple strings.
同じように、この関数、stringConcatenatorを複数のStringに適用できるんだ。
So for example, I can call string concatenator to say "I love" and then the string Scala.
例えば stringConcatenator("I love", "Scala") って呼べる。
And this will return the string "I love Scala".
そうすると "I love Scala" っていうStringが返ってくるよ。
So this is an example of a function with two arguments and a string return type.
これが引数2つでString戻り値の関数の例だね。
Good.
よし。
Now I'm going to show you some bits and pieces here about Scala as a functional programming language.
じゃあScalaの関数型プログラミング言語としての側面をいくつか見せていくよ。
First of all, I'm going to show you some syntax sugars.
まずはシンタックスシュガーから見せるね。
Syntax sugars means alternative syntax that will replace these much heavier boilerplate code.
シンタックスシュガーっていうのは、こういう重たいボイラープレートコードを置き換える別の構文のことだよ。
So I can create, for example, let's call this doubler, as a function 1 from int to int, as, watch what I'm writing, x colon int, arrow, and then I'm going to say 2 times x.
例えば、doublerっていうのをFunction1[Int, Int]として作る。よく見てね。x: Int => 2 * x って書くよ。
So this is a function that takes an argument of type int and returns twice that.
これはIntの引数を受け取って、その2倍を返す関数だね。
And obviously I can call doubler on, say, number 4, and I would get 8, of course.
当然 doubler(4) って呼べば8が返ってくるよね。
So what I've done here with this very shorthand notation is I've basically defined a new function 1 with int and int, in which the apply method, so override def apply, takes an argument x as an int and returns to times that argument.
この省略記法でやったことは、基本的にnew Function1[Int, Int]を定義して、applyメソッド、つまりoverride def applyで引数xをIntで受け取って2倍を返すのと同じことなんだ。
So this shorthand notation is the equivalent of this much longer notation, which for large code bases is extremely hard to read.
この省略記法は、大きなコードベースだと極めて読みにくいこっちの長い記法と同じものなんだよ。
So this is equivalent to the much longer this guy.
つまりこれは、こっちのずっと長いやつと同じってこと。
Alright, so I hope this makes sense.
なるほどって思ってもらえたかな。
Another syntax sugar is related to the actual function type.
もう一つのシンタックスシュガーは、関数の型自体に関するものだよ。
So function 1, typed with int and int, is noted in Scala as int, arrow, int.
Function1[Int, Int]は、Scalaでは Int => Int って書ける。
So int, arrow, int, is equivalent to function 1 of int and int.
Int => Int は Function1[Int, Int] と同じってことだね。
So this is equivalent to the much longer val doubler of type function 1 of int and int, equals new function int int, and so on and so forth.
つまりこれは、val doubler: Function1[Int, Int] = new Function1[Int, Int]... っていう長い書き方と同じなんだ。
In fact, you can go as far as omit the type altogether, because the compiler is smart enough to infer that for you.
実は型自体を省略することもできるんだ。コンパイラが賢いから推論してくれるよ。
So notice what happens if I cut this out, the compiler is still happy with my code, and if I hover over this value, it'd notice int, arrow, int.
これを消してみても、コンパイラはコードに文句を言わないし、この値にカーソルを合わせると Int => Int って表示されるよ。
This is automatically inferred by the compiler.
コンパイラが自動で推論してくれるんだ。
But I'm going to put this here for your future reference when you look at the code again.
でも後でコードを見返すときのために、型は書いておくね。
Now, I mentioned before that the goal of functional programming is to be able to compose functions, pass functions along, eventually pass functions as arguments, or return functions as a result.
さっき言ったけど、関数型プログラミングの目標は、関数を合成したり、関数を渡したり、関数を引数にしたり、関数を結果として返すことなんだ。
Now, the methods or functions that take functions as arguments or return functions as results are called higher order functions.
関数を引数に取ったり、関数を結果として返したりするメソッドや関数のことを高階関数って呼ぶんだ。
So higher order functions, either take functions as arguments, or return functions as results, or both.
高階関数は、関数を引数に取るか、関数を結果として返すか、その両方をやるものだよ。
Let me give you some examples.
例を見せるね。
So if I create a mapped list from list123.map, map is a very special method on the list type in that it allows the passing of a function.
List(1, 2, 3).mapでmappedListを作ると、mapはListの特別なメソッドで、関数を渡せるんだ。
So notice the map expects a function from int to some other type.
mapはIntから別の型への関数を期待してるよね。
So I can put x arrow x plus 1.
だから x => x + 1 って書ける。
I don't even need to mention the type of x because the compiler automatically infers that x is an int because the list of 1, 2, 3 is a list of ints.
xの型を書く必要もないんだ。List(1, 2, 3)がIntのListだから、コンパイラが自動的にxはIntだって推論してくれる。
And this anonymous function that I've created, which is the equivalent of new function 1 with int and int and so on and so forth.
ここで作った無名関数は、new Function1[Int, Int]... って書くのと同じものなんだ。
This anonymous function is passed as argument to the map method.
この無名関数がmapメソッドに引数として渡されてるわけ。
And so the map method on the list type is called a higher order function.
だからListのmapメソッドは高階関数って呼ばれるんだよ。
Now, the return value of list123.map with this anonymous function is another list.
List(1, 2, 3).mapにこの無名関数を渡した戻り値は、別のListになるよ。
So if I go ahead and print line a mapped list, and I run this application, you will notice that this function is applied to every single element, 1, 2, 3, and we obtain 2, 3, 4 in another list.
mappedListをprintlnして実行すると、この関数が各要素1, 2, 3に適用されて、別のListとして2, 3, 4が得られるのがわかるよ。
And so the return type is a list of int.
戻り値の型はList[Int]だね。
Now, as I mentioned before in the object oriented video earlier, the application of a method on a list or on any object that is due to modify the original object will actually return another instance.
前のオブジェクト指向の動画でも言ったけど、リストやどんなオブジェクトに対してもメソッドを呼ぶと、元のオブジェクトを変更するんじゃなくて、実際には別のインスタンスが返ってくるんだ。
And so a mapped list that we obtain here is a very different list than the list123 on which I originally applied the map method.
だからここで得られるmappedListは、元のList(1, 2, 3)とはまったく別のListなんだよ。
So this variable higher order function is called flat map.
次に見せたい高階関数はflatMapだよ。
Let me give you an example.
例を見せるね。
A flat mapped list.
flatMappedListを作るよ。
As, let's say, list123.flatmap, and the flat map function takes as argument a function from int to another collection of a given type.
List(1, 2, 3).flatMapで、flatMapは引数としてIntから別の型のコレクションへの関数を受け取るんだ。
So let me give you an example.
例を見せるね。
Let's say that for every single element, x, that belongs to this list, so x is 123 in turn.
このリストの各要素xに対して、つまりxは順番に1, 2, 3になるわけだけど
And for every element, I will return another list, let's say x and 2 times x.
各要素に対して別のリスト、例えば List(x, 2 * x) を返すとする。
So for every element in this list, for every element in the list 123, applying this function will return another list.
つまりList(1, 2, 3)の各要素にこの関数を適用すると、それぞれ別のリストが返ってくる。
So I will obtain the lists12, the list24, and the list36.
List(1, 2)、List(2, 4)、List(3, 6)が得られるよね。
Now, flat map's job is to concatenate all these small lists into another big list.
flatMapの仕事は、これらの小さなリストを全部つなげて一つの大きなリストにすることなんだ。
So if I print line a flat mapped list, we will obtain the lists1224 and 36 concatenated into a single list.
flatMappedListをprintlnすると、List(1, 2, 2, 4, 3, 6)が一つのリストに結合されて出てくるよ。
So notice here, the list1224, 36, all in a single list.
ここを見て。1, 2, 2, 4, 3, 6が全部一つのリストに入ってるでしょ。
Flat map is used very, very often in practice.
flatMapは実務でものすごくよく使うよ。
Now, as you write some Scala code, and as you look at other people's code, you might notice the following quirky syntax.
Scalaのコードを書いたり他の人のコードを読んだりしてると、ちょっと変わった構文に気づくかもしれない。
Instead of passing this lambda as it is inside some parentheses, you might be seeing this alternative syntax,
こうやってラムダを丸括弧の中にそのまま渡す代わりに、別の構文を見かけることがあるんだ。
where you say list123.flatmap, and somebody opens a curly brace, and on another line they pass in the lambda.
List(1, 2, 3).flatMapの後に波括弧を開いて、次の行にラムダを書くっていうやつ。
And it's usually in the form of x arrow, and then on another line the returned value.
普通は x => って書いて、次の行に返り値を書く形だね。
This is alternative syntax.
これは別の構文なんだ。
And this is the same as dot map with x arrow list with x and 2 times x.
これは .map(x => List(x, 2 * x)) って書くのと同じこと。
Inside the regular parentheses that you've probably been used to from the other programming languages.
他のプログラミング言語で見慣れてる普通の丸括弧の中に書くのとね。
Now, another classical higher-order function that we normally use on collections is filtered.
もう一つのよく使う高階関数はfilterだよ。
So a filtered list.
filteredListを作ろう。
As, let's say, list12345, and let's say we want to filter out just the elements smaller than 3.
List(1, 2, 3, 4, 5)から、3以下の要素だけをフィルタリングしたいとする。
So, filter, filter takes a function from int to boolean.
filterはIntからBooleanへの関数を受け取るんだ。
And the return value, the return list, will contain just those values for which the predicate returns true.
返ってくるリストには、そのpredicate（述語）がtrueを返した値だけが入るよ。
So, I will say that for every x that is returned in the result, x must be less than or equal to 3.
つまり、結果に含まれる各xについて、x <= 3 でなければならない。
So, x less than or equal to 3 is an expression that returns a boolean.
x <= 3 はBooleanを返す式だよね。
x arrow x less than or equal to 3 is an anonymous function.
x => x <= 3 は無名関数だ。
Filter takes this anonymous function and returns a new list containing only those elements from the list12345,
filterがこの無名関数を受け取って、List(1, 2, 3, 4, 5)のうち
for which this expression returns true.
この式がtrueを返す要素だけを含む新しいリストを返すんだ。
So, this will contain just the list123.
だからList(1, 2, 3)だけが残る。
So, if I print line a filtered list, I should be seeing the list123, which is what you see here in the console.
filteredListをprintlnすると、List(1, 2, 3)が表示されるはず。コンソールに見えてるよね。
Now, I'm going to show you some alternative, even shorter syntax.
じゃあさらに短い別の構文を見せるよ。
If this wasn't short enough, Scala allows even shorter syntax.
これでも十分短くないって？Scalaはもっと短く書けるんだ。
And I will be writing as follows.
こう書くよ。
I'm going to say underscore less than or equal to 3.
_ <= 3 って書く。
Underscore less than or equal to 3 is equivalent to x arrow x less than or equal to 3.
_  x <= 3 と同じ意味なんだ。
The Scala people that wrote the Scala syntax probably thought that repeating x twice was too much typing.
Scalaの構文を作った人たちは、xを2回書くのはタイプしすぎだと思ったんだろうね。
Now, as I mentioned earlier, in Scala we usually work with immutable objects and immutable collections in this case.
さっきも言ったけど、Scalaでは普通、不変オブジェクトと不変コレクションを使うんだ。
So, every single application to map, flat map, or filter will always return another instance of a list.
だからmap、flatMap、filterを呼ぶたびに、必ず新しいListのインスタンスが返ってくる。
And so, because every single call to map, flat map, and filter returns another instance,
map、flatMap、filterの呼び出しが毎回新しいインスタンスを返すから
we can chain applications to map, flat map, and filter.
map、flatMap、filterの呼び出しをチェーンできるんだ。
Let me give you an example.
例を見せるね。
Let's say we want to create all the pairs between the numbers 123 and the letters A, B, and C.
数字の1, 2, 3と文字のA, B, Cのすべてのペアを作りたいとする。
So, we want all the combinations 1A, 1B, 1C, 2A, 2B, 2C, and 3A, 3B, 3C.
つまり1-A、1-B、1-C、2-A、2-B、2-C、3-A、3-B、3-Cの全組み合わせがほしい。
We want all the possible combinations.
すべての組み合わせだよ。
A way to do that in Scala is to map and flat map the lists 1, 2, 3, and the lists A, B, C.
Scalaでそれをやる方法は、List(1, 2, 3)とList("a", "b", "c")をmapとflatMapすることなんだ。
And here's how we could do that.
やり方はこうだよ。
So, let's create all pairs as the list 123 dot flat map.
allPairsをList(1, 2, 3).flatMapで作る。
Alright.
よし。
So, I'm going to call flat map on the list 1, 2, 3.
List(1, 2, 3)に対してflatMapを呼ぶよ。
And for every single element, 1, 2, 3, I will return another small list.
各要素1, 2, 3に対して、別の小さなリストを返すんだ。
For example, if I take the element 1, I should return the smallest 1A, 1B, and 1C.
例えば要素1を取ったら、1-A、1-B、1-Cっていう小さなリストを返すべきだよね。
So, I will need to run a map on the list A, B, C.
だからList("a", "b", "c")に対してmapを実行する必要がある。
This is a lot to handle in your head.
頭の中で考えるとちょっと大変だよね。
So, I'm going to write some code and hopefully it will make sense as I write.
コードを書いていくから、書きながら理解してもらえればいいかな。
So, for every single element belonging to this numbers list, I'm actually going to call this number just to be a little bit more explicit.
この数字リストの各要素に対して、わかりやすいようにnumberって名前にするね。
So, for every number, I will run the list A, B, and C.
各numberに対して、List("a", "b", "c")を使うよ。
Let me collapse my menu so that you can see my code a little bit more clearly.
メニューを閉じてコードが見やすいようにするね。
So, for every number, I'm going to take the list A, B, C, and I'm going to prepend this number to every single letter.
各numberに対して、List("a", "b", "c")を取って、各文字の前にこのnumberをくっつけるんだ。
So, I'm going to call map, and for every letter, I'm going to return the string composing of the number.
mapを呼んで、各letterに対してnumberを含む文字列を返すよ。
So, I'm going to inject that in an S interpolated string.
s補間文字列にnumberを埋め込むんだ。
So, I'm going to say S quote, and with a dollar sign, I'm going to inject the number.
s"..." って書いて、$でnumberを埋め込む。
Let me say I'm going to put a dash here, and I'm going to also add the letter.
ここにダッシュを入れて、letterも追加するよ。
Alright, so I'm going to say 1A, 1B, and 1C for every single number in the original list.
こうすると元のリストの各numberに対して1-A、1-B、1-Cが得られるんだ。
And that will be the same for the list number 2, and for the list number 3.
number 2のリスト、number 3のリストも同じようになる。
And because I'm calling flat map, all these small lists will be concatenated into one big list.
flatMapを呼んでるから、これらの小さなリストが全部一つの大きなリストに結合されるよ。
list. So if I print line all pairs, you should be pleased of what you're going to see in the
allPairsをprintlnすると、いい結果が見れるはずだよ。
console. So we have the list 1a, 1b, 1c, 2a, 2b, 2c, and 3a, 3b, 3c. So notice how we can quote-unquote
コンソールを見て。1-a、1-b、1-c、2-a、2-b、2-c、3-a、3-b、3-cのリストになってるね。forループを使わずに
iterate through collections without using for loops, without using any kind of looping or
コレクションを「イテレート」できてるのがわかるでしょ。ループもイテレーションも
iteration. We're just calling maps, flatmaps, and maybe filtering if we want to pass in some
一切使ってない。map、flatMap、あとは条件を付けたいならfilterを呼んでるだけなんだ。
conditions on those numbers. So again, I'm calling flatmap on the original list such that for every
もう一回言うと、元のリストにflatMapを呼んで、各numberに対して
number I'm returning another small list. And that small list is obtained by this expression in which
別の小さなリストを返してる。その小さなリストはこの式で得られて、
for every single letter containing in the list a, b, c, I am prepending that number to that letter.
List("a", "b", "c")の各letterの前にnumberを付けてるんだ。
So I hope that makes sense. Now, in big Scala codebases, chains such as this one are increasingly
わかったかな。大きなScalaのコードベースだと、こういうチェーンはロジックが複雑になるほど
hard to read if the logic is increasingly complex. And so the Scala syntax allows for a pretty human
読みにくくなるんだよね。そこでScalaの構文では、mapやflatMapやfilterのチェーンを
readable chains of maps and flatmaps and filters in what we call for comprehensions. So let me give you
人間が読みやすい形で書けるfor内包表記っていうのがあるんだ。
an example, an equivalent example to the one that I just wrote. Let's call this alternative pairs
さっき書いたのと同じ例を見せるね。alternativePairsとして
as being for. So for is a keyword in Scala, but that does not mean for loops. This is a for comprehension
forって書く。forはScalaのキーワードだけど、forループじゃないよ。これはfor内包表記で、
and the for comprehension is an expression that we are going to attribute to this value. So watch what I'm
この値に代入する式なんだ。よく見ててね。
writing here. I'm going to say for number, left arrow, left, thin arrow. So look at this error in list one, two, three.
for の中に number <- List(1, 2, 3) って書く。この左向き矢印ね。
On another row, I'm going to say letter in the list a, b, and c.
次の行に letter <- List("a", "b", "c") って書く。
I'm going to say yield the string at the s interpolated string number dash letter.
そしてyieldで s"$number-$letter" っていうs補間文字列を返す。
This for expression over here is a single expression that can be reduced to a value. In this case,
このfor式は一つの式で、値に還元できるんだ。この場合は
the list 1a, 1b, 1c, 2a, 2b, 2c, and 3a, 3b, 3c. This is equivalent
1-a、1-b、1-c、2-a、2-b、2-c、3-a、3-b、3-cのリストになる。これは
to the map flatmap chain
上で書いたmapとflatMapのチェーンと
above. So whenever the compiler sees a for comprehension, it will actually deconstruct that
同じなんだ。コンパイラはfor内包表記を見ると、上で書いたのと同じように
into a chain of flatmaps and maps in much the same way as I wrote above. In fact,
flatMapとmapのチェーンに分解するんだよ。実際
these two expressions are identical to the compiler. This kind of chaining of maps, flatmaps, filtering,
この2つの式はコンパイラにとってまったく同じもの。map、flatMap、filter、for内包表記のチェーンは
and for comprehensions will prove particularly useful in whatever collections you might have to deal
どんなコレクションを扱う場面でも特に便利だよ。
with. And you will probably deal with a lot of collections. If you're working in a parallel or
コレクションはたくさん扱うことになるからね。並列や
distributed environment, if you're working with Spark data frames or with resilient distributed data sets or
分散環境で作業したり、SparkのDataFrameやRDD（Resilient Distributed Dataset）を扱ったり、
whatever kind of linear, multidimensional, parallel distributed collections you might work with,
線形、多次元、並列分散どんな種類のコレクションを使うにしても、
this kind of mapping, flatmapping, filtering, and for comprehension skills will prove useful there.
map、flatMap、filter、for内包表記のスキルが役に立つよ。
Speaking of collections, let me show you a couple of collections.
コレクションの話が出たから、いくつかのコレクションを見せるね。
So first, I'm going to show you lists. They are the fundamental collection of functional programming.
まずはList。関数型プログラミングの基本的なコレクションだよ。
So I'm going to define a list as, let's say, list one, two, three, four, five.
ListをList(1, 2, 3, 4, 5)で定義するよ。
The map flatmap filter will work for all the collections that I'm going to list. So I'm not going to
map、flatMap、filterはこれから紹介するすべてのコレクションで使えるから、毎回は
mention them every single time. The list has the property that it has a head and a tail.
説明しないね。Listにはheadとtailっていうプロパティがあるんだ。
The head is the first element of the list. The tail is the remainder of the list.
headはリストの最初の要素。tailはリストの残り。
So I'm going to call this first element as a list dot head and val rest as a list dot tail.
firstElementをaList.headで、restをaList.tailで取得するよ。
So head and tail are the fundamental operations on list.
headとtailがListの基本操作なんだ。
Lists can be prepended and appended with elements. So I'm going to say a prepended list
Listには要素を先頭や末尾に追加できるよ。prependedListを作ると
as let's say zero prepended to a list. The colon colon operator is applicable to a list.
例えば0をリストの先頭に追加する。:: 演算子がListに使えるんだ。
In this particular case, we will return the list zero, one, two, three, four, five.
この場合、List(0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5)が返ってくるよ。
Let's call this an added list or let's say an extended list.
extendedListも作ろう。
We can prepend and append elements with some very special operators. Let's say zero plus column a list,
特別な演算子で要素を先頭や末尾に追加できる。0 +: aList :+ 6 みたいに、
colon plus let's say the number six, plus colon prepends an element to a list, colon plus appends
+: は要素をリストの先頭に追加、:+ は要素をリストの
an element to a list. And so the result will be the list zero, one, two, three, four, five, six.
末尾に追加する。だから結果はList(0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6)になるよ。
So that's with lists. Let me show you sequences.
Listはこんな感じ。次はSequenceを見せるね。
Sequences are denoted by the type seek. So seq, let's call this a sequence as seek of int.
SequenceはSeqっていう型で表されるよ。aSequenceをSeq[Int]として
So seq and seq has a constructor seek. Let's call this one, two, three. And the seek is actually,
Seq(1, 2, 3)って作る。Seqは実は
as you probably know from object orientation, seek dot apply. So seek has a companion object,
オブジェクト指向で学んだように、Seq.applyなんだ。Seqにはコンパニオンオブジェクトがあって、
which has an apply method that takes these arguments and it will return an instance deriving
そのapplyメソッドがこれらの引数を受け取って、Seq traitを継承した
from the seek trait. So seek is actually a trait. It's an abstract type. And this apply factory method
インスタンスを返すんだ。Seqは実はtrait、つまり抽象型で、このapplyファクトリメソッドが
will actually return an instance of a derived type from sequence. The main characteristic of a sequence is
Sequenceの派生型のインスタンスを返す。Sequenceの主な特徴は
that you can access an element at a given index. So let's call this accessed element as a sequence
インデックスで要素にアクセスできること。accessedElementとしてaSequence.applyに
dot apply. And you can pass in an index, let's say the index one. Now, you know, the apply method is
インデックス、例えば1を渡す。applyメソッドはオブジェクトを関数のように呼び出せるから
allowing an object to be invoked like a function. So we can remove that altogether. And that will be the
.applyを省略しても同じだよね。
same thing. So applying a sequence to an index will return the number at that index. So the element at index
Sequenceにインデックスを適用すると、そのインデックスの要素が返ってくる。インデックス1の要素は
one, which in our case, that's two. All right. So that was sequences, a particular type of sequence, which is
この場合2だね。Sequenceはこんな感じ。大きなデータに対してとても高速な特別なSequenceが
very fast for large data is vectors. So val a vector is vector, let's say one, two, three, four, five, and so on and so forth.
Vectorだよ。aVectorとしてVector(1, 2, 3, 4, 5)みたいに作る。
Vector has very fast access time and has the exact same methods as lists or sequences. So I'm going to call this
Vectorはアクセス時間がとても速くて、ListやSequenceとまったく同じメソッドが使える。
fast sequence implementation.
高速なSequenceの実装ってことだね。
All right. So that was list sequences vectors. Let me show you sets.
よし。List、Sequence、Vectorはこんな感じ。次はSetを見せるよ。
So sets are collections with no duplicates.
Setは重複のないコレクションだよ。
So if I define a set as set applied to the numbers one, two, three, four, one, two, three,
Set(1, 2, 3, 4, 1, 2, 3)って定義すると、
because I've added the numbers one, two, three twice, they will appear only once in the resulting set.
1, 2, 3を2回追加してるけど、結果のSetには1回しか出てこない。
So this will be the set one, two, three, four.
つまりSet(1, 2, 3, 4)になるんだ。
Now, the main property of a set and the fundamental method of a set is to test whether an element is
Setの主なプロパティと基本メソッドは、要素がSetに含まれてるかテストすること。
contained in the set. So let's say val set has five as a set dot contains the number five.
例えば setHasFive として aSet.contains(5) とすると
And this will be false because the number five is not contained in the set.
5はSetに含まれてないからfalseになるよ。
So the contains method is actually a method that returns true or false whether the argument is
containsメソッドは引数がSetに含まれてるかどうかでtrueかfalseを返すんだ。
actually contained in the set or not. You can actually add more elements to the set by calling
要素を追加したり削除したりもできるよ。
the plus or remove the elements with the minus method. So let's say an added set as a set plus five.
+で追加、-で削除だね。例えば anAddedSet = aSet + 5 とする。
You know by now that plus is actually a method name from the int type.
+が実はメソッド名だってもうわかってるよね。Int型のだけじゃなくて、
And the plus method is also available on the set type which returns the set one, two, three, four, five.
+メソッドはSet型でも使えて、Set(1, 2, 3, 4, 5)が返ってくる。
Not necessarily in this order because the order is not important in a set collection.
必ずしもこの順番とは限らないけどね。Setでは順序は重要じゃないから。
Let's call this a removed set as a set minus the number let's say three.
aRemovedSetとして aSet - 3 とすると
So with the minus sign you can remove an element out of the collection.
マイナス記号でコレクションから要素を削除できるんだ。
So you can say set one, two and four. The number three is removed.
Set(1, 2, 4)になる。3が削除されたね。
So that was sets.
Setはこんな感じ。
Another very useful collection that we work with in day to day is ranges.
日常的にとても便利なもう一つのコレクションがRangeだよ。
This is useful for quote unquote iteration.
いわゆる「イテレーション」に便利なんだ。
Although obviously we use map and flat map to work on the ranges.
もちろんRangeに対してもmapやflatMapを使って操作するけどね。
So let me define a range as one, two, one thousand.
Rangeを 1 to 1000 で定義するよ。
One, two, one thousand is a fictitious collection that does not contain all the numbers between one
1 to 1000 は、1から1000までの全数字を実際には持ってないフィクションのコレクションだけど
and one thousand, but it can be processed as if it did.
持ってるかのように処理できるんだ。
So if I want all the numbers between two and two thousand in two by two increments,
2から2000までの2刻みの全数字がほしいなら
I can say let's call this two by two as a range dot map.
twoByTwoとして aRange.map って書いて
And I can pass in a function, an anonymous function, x arrow two times x.
無名関数 x => 2 * x を渡せばいい。
Or if you're really fancy, you can say two times underscore.
おしゃれに書きたいなら 2 * _ って書けるよ。
And then you can call to list.
そして .toList を呼ぶ。
And this will be the list of all the elements between two and two thousand that are
こうすると2から2000までの偶数の
even.
リストが得られるんだ。
So we can obtain the list two, four, six, eight, and so on and so forth up to two thousand.
List(2, 4, 6, 8, ...)みたいに2000まで得られるよ。
Now notice I use the to list method.
toListメソッドを使ったのに注目してね。
You can use to list, to set, to sequence, to convert in between all these collections.
toList、toSet、toSeqを使ってコレクション間の変換ができるんだ。
In particular, to list is very useful.
特にtoListは便利だよ。
It can be called on any other collection and convert that to a list.
どんなコレクションからでも呼べてListに変換してくれる。
Also very useful are tuples, which are essentially groups of values under the same value.
あと便利なのがタプルで、これは複数の値を一つの値にまとめたものだよ。
You Python users will probably appreciate this.
Pythonを使ってる人にはお馴染みだよね。
So let's call a tuple as the tuple, let's say Bon Jovi,
タプルを作るには、例えば ("Bon Jovi",
the string rock or classical rock and 1982 or something like that.
"Rock" とか "Classical Rock" と 1982) みたいに書く。
So these bits of information are grouped under the single value, a tuple,
これらの情報が一つの値、タプルにまとめられていて
and the tuple is delimited by the simple parentheses.
タプルは普通の丸括弧で区切られるんだ。
And finally, maps.
最後にMap。
You've surely seen maps before.
Mapは見たことあるよね。
There are associations between some keys and some values.
キーと値の対応関係を表すものだよ。
So I'm going to define a map as a map, let's say, between string and int.
Map[String, Int]として定義するよ。
Let's say I want to define a phone book.
電話帳を作りたいとする。
Let's say I have a one phone book.
aPhonebookを作ろう。
This will be constructed as a map, so notice I'm calling the apply method on the companion object of map,
Mapで構築するよ。Mapのコンパニオンオブジェクトのapplyメソッドを呼んでて、
and we can pass in any kind of two argument tuples.
2要素のタプルを渡せるんだ。
So I can say Daniel has the phone number whatever, and Jane has the phone number whatever else.
"Daniel"の電話番号はこれ、"Jane"の電話番号はこれ、みたいに書ける。
Finally, tuples can also be expressed in terms of Jane thin arrow this number,
ちなみにタプルは "Jane" -> 番号 って矢印で書くこともできて
which is equivalent to the regular tuple Jane and that same number.
これは ("Jane", 番号) っていう普通のタプルと同じなんだ。
So 327285.
327285ね。
All right, we're done.
よし、ここまでだよ。
All right.
よし。
So in this video, you've learned about Scala as a functional programming language.
この動画では、Scalaの関数型プログラミング言語としての側面を学んだね。
I hope this video was useful, and I'll be waiting for you in the next one.
この動画が役に立ってたら嬉しいな。次の動画で待ってるよ。
If you liked this video and found it useful, go ahead and click the like button
この動画が良かったら、いいねボタンを押して
and subscribe to the Rock the JVM channel, and I'll be posting more free goodies here.
Rock the JVMチャンネルを登録してね。もっと無料コンテンツを出していくよ。
This video series is also available as a free online course at rockthejvm.com,
この動画シリーズはrockthejvm.comで無料オンラインコースとしても公開してて
where you will also have the option to download these videos for your offline use.
そこではオフラインで使えるように動画をダウンロードすることもできるよ。
And on the Rock the JVM site, we also have hundreds of hours of premium content
Rock the JVMのサイトには、Scala、関数型プログラミング、
dedicated to Scala, functional programming, Akka, Apache Spark, and so much more.
Akka、Apache Sparkなどの数百時間のプレミアムコンテンツもあるよ。
So go ahead and check out rockthejvm.com, and I'll be waiting for you in the next video.
ぜひrockthejvm.comをチェックしてね。次の動画で待ってるよ。